Aki Fukai Product Designer Curriculum Vitae

Last updated: June 2022

Availability

I'm available as a freelancer on a project or contract base to together shape focused teams within agencies, startups and agile enterprises who want to launch or improve their digital customer experience. I'm collaborating effectively mostly remote since 2019.

As a Swiss citizen I'm currently live with my family

in Hamburg Germany.

Contact

Cell DE: +49 172 431 15 00

Email: aki@fukai.ch Web: fukai.ch

Nationality: Swiss

Current residence: Hamburg, Germany

Twitter: @FUKAldesign **Profile on:** LinkedIn

Profile on: Xing

Page Index

Contact Details & Current Situation p. 1
About Me & Digital Products p. 2
Selected Clients & Agencies p. 3
Work Experience & Education p. 4
Project Highlights p. 4-5

About Me

With my work I strive to **improve people's lives** by solving complex problems with simple and useful solutions. By shaping technology into thoughtful digital products that matter I work towards the answers — for the people who use it and the people who provide and grow it — with engineers, product/business people, domain experts and real users.

My tools are user research, UX consulting, interaction design and user interface design. I have been developing concepts, strategies and designs focused on web based products and services including mobile since 1998.

I believe the best results emerge from a **close collaboration**, be it in internal interdisciplinary teams, or through a consultancy in a **committed relationship** with clients.

In my spare time I am with **my family**, travel and learn from different cultures and practice Chen Style Taiji. I love clean and useful (Swiss) typography, **minimal** and **'super normal' design** and **learning new things** in live and in my profession.

I am a **native German speaker** of Swiss and Japanese heritage. I am **fluent in English** and have an advanced basic knowledge of **French**.

Selected Clients in alphabetical order

academics.de (Die Zeit, Forschung & Lehre)

Audi

Beiersdorf (Eucerin)

Baden-Württemberg Ministry of State

Bentley

BMW (bmw.com)

Chrysler (Jeep, Chrysler)

collectAl (Liquid Labs / Otto Group)

CTS Eventim AG

Daimler / Mercedes-Benz

Deutsche Bahn AG

dtp entertainment AG

enfore AG

Gameplay

Hello Meet

JPC

Klinikum Südstadt Rostock

KRAFT Foods (Milka, Kraft)

LG Electronics

natcon7 (part of Nordex)

Netbreeze (now part of Microsoft)

Otto Reisen, Reiseland

PlasticPlan (MVPF)

receeve GmbH

Rossmann

SAP SE

SBB Informatik AG

Scout24 Schweiz AG

Siemens Medical Solutions

Sony Deutschland

Sqoops, Doomster (doomster.de) until 11.2008

STURM und DRANG (partner of MetaDesign)

Telefónica Germany (o2)

Tipp-Kick

Trilux

Unify (formerly Siemens Enterprise Communications)

University of Applied Sciences, Dept of Design HAW, Hamburg

Various medium-sized companies and multinational groups of different branches and municipal institutions

Selected Agencies in alphabetical order

brink & martens GmbH

D-LABS GmbH

DDD Design GmbH

EYELABEL Digital Communication

Freiland Netzlösungen GmbH

frog design

Häberlein & Mauerer AG

IconMedialab AG

Interone GmbH

Jung von Matt/next

Kabel New Media AG

Neue Digitale Razorfish GmbH

Nolte & Lauth GmbH

OgilvvInteractive

Philipp und Keuntje

Plan.Net

STURM und DRANG, Innovation Insights

superReal GmbH (part of DEPT®)

TEMPODOME GmbH

WowBiz GmbH

Work Experience

2004 - today

Freelance product designer (UX/UI), concept

developer/consultant IA/UX

Startups: i.a. PlasticPlan, enfore AG, Liquid Labs **Companies:** i.a. SBB, SAP, Daimler, Telefónica, SMB

& DACH and global brands

02.2022 - today

Freelance lead product designer Client: PlasticPlan

06.2020 - today

Partner & senior product designer App: Hello Meet

06.2018 - 05.2020

(Freelance) sr. product designer Client: enfore AG

02.2016 - 02.2018

(Freelance) senior interaction designer

Client: collectAl (at Liquid Labs/Otto Group)

11.2015 - 09.2016 (40-60%)

Freelance sr. interaction designer Client: SBB

07.2015 - 10.2015

Freelance sr. interaction designer Client: SAP SE

02.2015 - 04.2015

Senior user experience designer

Client: Scout24 Schweiz AG

12.2013 - 10.2014

Freelance senior interaction designer

Client: natcon7 GmbH

09.2013 - 01.2014

Freelance senior interaction designer

Agency: frog design Client: Unify (Siemens)

01.2013 - 04.2013

Freelance UX designer Client: Immonet

05.2011 - 09.2011

Freelance sr. art director / design lead

Agency: Razorfish Client: Telefónica (o2)

2008 - 2013 (intermittent)

Freelance art director, IxD, UX consultant

Agency: WowBiz GmbH Clients i.a.: Aquila Capital,

Rossmann, Netbreeze

2006 - 2008

Freelance art-/creative director, designer

Agency: DDD Design GmbH Clients i.a.: Audi,

DaimlerChrysler (Mercedes-Benz, Jeep, Chrysler,

Dodge), jpc.de, lesen.de 2003 - 2004

Art director Agency: Spirit Link GmbH

Clients: SiemensMedical Solutions, Siemens, the agency's relaunch (website and PM software)

2001 - 2002

Art director and designer

Agency: GiveMe5 Online-Kommunikation GmbH **Clients i.a.:** Bentley, Curtius Lütten von Perfall

Werbeagentur GmbH, Otto Reisen, Reiseland

2000 - 2001

Screen designer, UI designer

Agency: IconMedialab AG

Clients i.a.: FMCG, intranet applications, various usability focused projects and web specials

2000 - 2000

Freelance screen designer

Agency: Ahead Deutschland, now Valtech

Clients i.a.: FMCG, i.a. Milka

1998 - 2000

Freelance screen designer

Agency: Kabel New Media AG

Client: BMW.com

1997 - 1997

Screen designer (internship)

Agency: Fork Unstable Media

Clients i.a.: Learning on lifestyle magazine 'blond',

Spar and others

Education

1994 - 1998

HAW Hamburg, Fakultät Design, Medien und

Information / Department Design:

Kommunikationsdesign / communication design

Project Highlights

For a more visual look at projects until 04.2015 take a look at my **PDF portfolio** (to be updated)

Making plastic packaging sustainable, with data – Plastic Plan

Duration: 02.2022 - today

Done: Designing the human centred interface on top of an Al-supported data service empowering enterprises to manage complex packaging data transparently & enabling teams across units to make product packaging sustainable,

Technology: Web, Vue.js, Tailwind **Role:** Lead product designer

Group scheduling made simple – Hello Meet

Duration: 01.2018 - today

Done: Hypothesis driven product design and development, JTBD based user flows and UIs, new features, continuous improvement, co-shaping

and testing the business model **Technology:** iOS, Android, Web, React **Role:** Partner & senior product designer

Helping local stores to run their businesses – enfore AG

Duration: 06.2018 - 05.2020

Done: Reservations, pick-up & delivery and dashboard widgets in enforePOS, online presence,

email & business documents

Technology: Web/mail (responsive), enforeDasher,

enforeDonner

Role: Senior product designer

End-to-end digital collections, redefined – collectAl

Duration: 02.2016 - 02.2018

Done: White label digital self-service dunning, collections & payment processes, merchant portal **Technology:** Web/mail (respons.), iOS, iPad, React

Role: Senior product designer

iPad and web/desktop app for SBB based on GIS technology

Duration: 11.2015 - 09.2016

Done: UX concept, flows, mockups, prototypes

(Sketch/InVision)

Technology: Web (responsive), iOS, iPad

Role: Senior interaction designer

Fiori App Finder for SAP Global Design

Duration: 07.2015 - 10.2015

Done: UX concepts, flows, Prototypes (Axure RP Pro), Fiori UX design guidelines for App Finder &

Fiori Launchpad

Technology: Web (responsive), iOS, iPhone

Role: Senior interaction designer **Direct client** (with D-Labs)

Unify Project Ansible – platform for unified enterprise communication

Duration: 09.2013 - 02.2014

Done: Conceived and documented the interaction design throughout (web and mobile) for various features e.g. conferencing, voice/video calls in collaboration with the client – from overarching

concepts to detailed UI states

Technology: Web (responsive), iOS, iPhone

Role: Senior interaction designer

With: frog design

Social Media Summary for Netbreeze -

a Swiss ETH spin-off, acquired by Microsoft 2013

Duration: 05.2012 - 06.2012

Done: High level concept incl. visualisation of an exemplary core screens based on a timeline UI – for the Swiss social media monitoring startup **Role:** Concept developer (IA/UX), UX designer, art

director & UI designer

With: WowBiz

Comprehensive telco portal and e-commerce relaunch of o2.de

(Telefónica Germany)

Duration: 05.2011 - 10.2011

Done: Simplification of the shopping flow, Optimisation of the checkout process UX, Unified teaser concept, Tablet/touch enabled, Client side UX consultation, Brand alignment,

Style guide

Role: Senior art director and design lead

With: Neue Digitale / Razorfish